Finding Aid for History and Traditions of the University Committee (University of Michigan) interviews, 1991-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
History and Traditions of the University Committee (University of Michigan) interviews 1991-2004
University of Michigan. History and Traditions of the University Committee.
5.5 lin. ft.
93817 Bimu 2
University committee appointed the president to facilitate the preservation, promotion, and appreciation of the history and traditions. Material includes oral history interviews with university presidents and their wives, administrative and academic officers, regents and faculty members.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The interviews and other materials were donated by the Committee (donor no. 8075 ) in multiple accessions.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The records are open for research except for interviews for which releases were not obtained.
The University Committee on History and Traditions was appointed by University of Michigan President James J. Duderstadt in 1991 to facilitate the preservation, promotion, and appreciation of the history and traditions of the University of Michigan as a leading institution of higher learning and education. Some of the activities the committee has undertaken in order to promote aspects of the university’s history include a marker program, an oral history program, and the presentation of certificates of recognition to persons and units for their contributions to the celebration of the university’s history.
The committee also works with university schools, colleges, departments, and units in activities to promote their history, as well as facilitating a variety of activities related to the preservation of historic artifacts, and providing advice and guidance to the university administration and the university community in general on many issues related to history and traditions. Reappointed by President Lee Bollinger in 1998, the History and Traditions Committee continues its work under the guidance of President Mary Sue Coleman.
The History and Traditions Committee website: http://www.umich.edu/pres/history/
The History and Traditions committee records consist of interviews (audio-tapes and transcripts) with University of Michigan presidents, wives of presidents, regents, and administrators, including Allan and Alene Smith, Anne and Harlan Hatcher, Robben and Sally Fleming, Harold and Vivian Shapiro, Robert Forman, Richard Kennedy, Gertrude E. Huebner, Thomas Roach, James F. Brinkerhoff, Peter O. Steiner, and Wilber Pierpont; also videocassettes of conversation with University of Michigan presidents Harlan Hatcher, Robben Fleming, Allan Smith, Harold Shapiro, and James Duderstadt; also visual materials.
The records include two videocassettes entitled, "An Afternoon with the Presidents" (U-matic) consisting of a joint interview conducted by Robert Warner with presidents and acting presidents of the University of Michigan; and "University of Michigan Scrapbook," (VHS) consisting of a historical sketch of the university.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan--History--20th century.; University of Michigan. President.; University of Michigan--Presidents.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Oral histories.; University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan--History--20th century.; University of Michigan--Presidents.; University of Michigan. President.; Sound recordings.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan--History--20th century.; University of Michigan. President.; University of Michigan--Presidents.; Afternoon with the presidents.; Duderstadt, James J., 1942-; Fleming, R. W. (Robben Wright), 1916-; Hatcher, Harlan Henthorne, 1898-; Shapiro, Harold T., 1935-; Smith, Allan Frederick, 1911-; Warner, Robert M. (Robert Mark), 1927-2007.; University of Michigan scrapbook.
Contributors:
Brinkerhoff, James F.; Duderstadt, James J., 1942-; Fleming, R. W. (Robben Wright), 1916-; Fleming, Sally.; Forman, Robert G.; Hatcher, Anne.; Hatcher, Harlan Henthorne, 1898-; Huebner, Gertrude, 1915-; Kennedy, Richard L.; Pierpont, Wilbur K., 1914-; Roach, Thomas A., 1929-; Shapiro, Harold T., 1935-; Shapiro, Vivian.; Smith, Allan Frederick, 1911-; Smith, Alene.; Steiner, Peter Otto, 1922-
Genre Terms:
Oral histories.; Videotapes.
- Interviews with University of Michigan Presidents and wives, administrators, and regents
  - Transcripts of interviews
    - Brinkerhoff, James, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Fleming, Robben W., 1992 (Box 1)
    - Fleming, Sally, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Forman, Robert G., 1995-1996 (Box 1)
    - Hatcher, Anne, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Hatcher, Harlan H., 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Huebner, Gertrude E., 2003 (Box 1)
    - Kennedy, Richard L., 1995 (Box 1)
    - Pierpont, Wilbur K., 1996 (Box 2)
    - Roach, Thomas A., 2004 (Box 2)
    - Shapiro, Harold, 1993 (Box 2)
      (restricted; closed pending return of release form; in box 6)
    - Shapiro, Vivian, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Smith, Alene, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Smith, Allan F., 1992 (Box 2)
    - Steiner, Peter, 1994 (Box 2)
- Visual materials
  - Videotape:
    - "An Afternoon with the Presidents," November 1992, 2 U-matic videotapes (Box 2)
    - "The University of Michigan Scrapbook," ca. 1994-1995, 3 vhs videotapes (Box 2)
- Duplicates of transcripts; audiotapes and compact discs of interviews
  - Transcripts (duplicate copies) (Box 3)
  - Audiotapes and compact discs of interviews (Box 4)
  - Duplicate copies of audiotapes and compact discs (Box 5)
  - Interviews temporarily closed pending return of release form (Box 6)